Guide to the Special Righteousness Committee collection 1980-2002
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Special Righteousness Committee collection
1980-2002
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 2988-20
Special Righteousness Committee (Portland, Or.)
1 cubic foot 1 document case, 1 flat box, and 1 oversize folder
Materials created by an Oregon organization opposed to the Oregon Citizens Alliance and the anti-gay Measure 9 in 1992, including humorous political art work. Also includes materials related to the Radical Faeries and other organizations.
Historical Note
The Special Righteousness Committee came about in opposition to the Oregon Citizens Alliance (OCA) and their 1992 Oregon Ballot Measure 9. This measure would have amended the Oregon state constitution to define homosexuality as "abnormal" and "wrong," and would have prevented any protections of lesbian and gay citizens under state laws. The Special Righteousness Committee -- whose name was derived from the OCA's slogan "no special rights" -- used humor and elaborately illustrated graphics to lampoon the OCA initiative. The group facetiously supported additional constitutional amendments based on admonishments within the biblical book of Leviticus, such as "No special rights for oyster eaters."
The collection includes: illustrated certificates, original artworks, newsletters and brochures, signs and posters, graphic art booklets, excerpts from the 1992 Oregon Voter's Pamphlet, State of Oregon Statewide Initiative Petition forms, and materials documenting the Oregon Citizens Alliance and Lon Mabon. The collection also includes "Lon Mabon Cut Out Dolls" illustrated by Vaughn Frick. Also included are a small quantity of materials related to the Radical Faeries of the Pacific Northwest.
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series A: Special Righteousness Committee materials
Series B: Radical Faeries and other related materials
The collection is open to the public.
Materials were found at a garage sale in Portland, Oregon, by George Nicola of the Gay and Lesbian Archives of the Pacific Northwest, and donated to the Oregon Historical Society.
Acquired June 2013, Library Accession 27956
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Frick, Vaughn
Special Righteousness Committee--Archives; Oregon Citizens Alliance; Gay and Lesbian Archives of the Pacific Northwest; Radical Faeries (New Age movement)
Oregon--Politics and government--1951-
Gays--Oregon; Lesbians--Oregon
Gays and Lesbians; Oregon; Political Campaigns
Cartoons (humorous images); Political cartoons
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Special Righteousness Committee Materials, Series A
  - 1992 Voter's Pamphlet Text (Box-folder 1/1)
    Page 95 of the Official 1992 General Voters' Pamphlet as supplied to Oregon voters. Special Righteousness Committee paid for a statement in support of Ballot Measure 9. Text uses a literal interpretation of the biblical book of Leviticus in order to point out the hypocrisy of the OCA-sponsored ballot initiative. "[The state] promotes oyster-eating by licensing seafood restaurants..." etc.
  - Constitutional Amendment Petition Signature Sheet, 1992 (Box-folder OSA-1/1)
    Statewide Initiative Petition sheets "authorized and paid for by Special Righteousness Committee" in support of a constitutional amendment. "Summary: Amends Oregon Constitution. Declares eating certain foods (including shrimp, lobster, clams, rabbit, pork, rare steak and chocolate ants), crossbreeding cattle, wearing clothing of more than one fabric, shaving beards, adultery without punishment of death, cursing one's parents without punishment of death 'abnormal, unnatural, perverse, immoral and generally disgusting conduct.'"
  - Indulgence Poster, 1992 (Box-folder OSA-1/2)
    Original artwork and colored copies of Special Righteousness Committee posters presented to financial supporters.
  - The Laws of Ritual Holiness from Leviticus, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Handout quoting select verses from the biblical book of Leviticus, admonishing against various dietary, social, and sexual practices.
  - License to Discriminate, circa 1992 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Illustrated certificates with a space for entering the bearer's name. "This license certifies that [____] has hereby been granted the special right to discriminate against O.C.A. members on the basis of his/her sincere and deeply held moral belief that these people are repugnant hypocrites."
  - Lon Mabon Cut Out Doll, 2000, 2002 (Box-folder OSA-1/3)
    Original sketches, color artwork, and illustrations for satirical paper doll & costumes lampooning Lon Mabon. Also includes a follow up costume after Mabon was imprisoned for contempt of court. "Concept: M. Dennis Moore and Vaughn Frick. Copyright 2000 by Family Alliance of GOD (FAG)."
  - No Special Rights Sign, circa 1992 (Box-folder Oversize Folder)
    Cardboard sign: "No Special Rights For Oyster Eaters!"
  - Quotations from Chairman Mabon (2002) (Box-folder 1/4)
    Compiled by M. Dennis Moore. A stapled handout documenting the OCA, Lon Mabon, Ballot Measure 9, and the parodies created by Special Righteousness Committee in response.
  - RIGHTEOUS "X" Goes to Hell, 1992 (Box-folder 1/7)
    Graphic novel-style brochures, illustrated by Vaughn Frick. Small, staple-bound handouts and an enlargement copy.
  - RIGHTEOUS "X" Goes to Hell Flats, 1992 (Box-folder OSA-1/5)
    Printer's flats for front & back cover of booklet distributed by Special Righteousness Committee.
  - SIN CREDIT Poster, undated (Box-folder OSA-1/6)
    Poster in response to Republican "pollution credits" concept. "[____] is hereby granted a credit of five thousand (5,000) sin units, equivalent to burning, for one year, in the Lake of Fire!" By Priscilla Normal.
  - SRC Booth Board, circa 1992 (Box-folder OSA-1/7)
    Cardboard display featuring copies of news articles about various efforts sponsored by Special Righteousness Committee.
  - Surrender Oyster-Eaters! (1992) (Box-folder 1/8)
    Two-sided handout "authorized by Special Righteousness Committee" elaborating on their efforts to promote additional constitutional amendments based on admonishments contained within the biblical book of Leviticus.
- Series B, Radical Faeries and other related materials
  - Radical Faerie Party Invitations, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Invitations to a 1984 Pride Party and a 1985 Rocky Horror Picture Show party at a private home in SE Portland.
  - Radical Faerie Publications (1984-1987) (Box-folder 1/6)
    Assorted brochures related to Radical Faeries in the Pacific Northwest.
    FaeryLand News (Vol. 1, No. 1): June 24, 1984 (San Francisco)
    The Faerie Home Companion (premier edition): circa 1987 (Seattle)
    Faerie Home Companion (Vol. 1, Issue 3): circa 1987 (Seattle)
    Directory - West Coast Faerie Symposium & Tea Dance, undated, cover only (Wolf Creek)
    Nomenus (No. 2): June 1985 (San Francisco)
    Handout from Equal Time Newspaper (circa 1986).
  - Somebody's Place Poster, 1980 (Box-folder OSA-1/6)
    Poster for a bar in SW Portland. "Celebrating the end of our 1st year, 1 March '80".